Denis R Newman-Griffis

Curriculum Vitae

Natural Language Processing, Disability and Occupational Health, Computational Semantics, Biomedical Informatics, Machine Learning

Publications

- *=equal contributor
 - 2019 Denis Newman-Griffis and Eric Fosler-Lussier. HARE: a Flexible Highlighting Annotator for Ranking and Exploration. In Proceedings of the 2019 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing: Systems Demonstrations.
 - 2019 **Denis Newman-Griffis***, Ayah Zirikly*, Guy Divita*, and Bart Desmet. Classifying the reported ability in clinical mobility descriptions. In *Proceedings of BioNLP 2019*, 2019.
 - 2019 Brendan Whitaker*, **Denis Newman-Griffis***, Aparajita Haldar*, Hakan Ferhatosmanoglu, and Eric Fosler-Lussier. Characterizing the impact of geometric properties of word embeddings on task performance. In *Proceedings of the Third Workshop on Evaluating Vector Space Representations for NLP*, 2019.
 - 2018 Denis Newman-Griffis and Ayah Zirikly. Embedding Transfer for Low-Resources Medical Named Entity Recognition: A Case Study on Patient Mobility. In *Proceedings of BioNLP*, 2018
 - 2018 Denis Newman-Griffis, Albert M Lai, and Eric Fosler-Lussier. Jointly Embedding Entities and Text with Distant Supervision. In Proceedings of the 3rd Workshop on Representation Learning for NLP (Repl4NLP), 2018.
 - 2017 Thanh Thieu, Jonathan Camacho, Pei-Shu Ho, Julia Porcino, Min Ding, Lisa Nelson, Elizabeth Rasch, Chunxiao Zhou, Leighton Chan, Diane Brandt, Denis Newman-Griffis, Ao Yuan, and Albert M Lai. Inductive identification of functional status information and establishing a gold standard corpus: A case study on the Mobility domain. In 2017 IEEE International Conference on Bioinformatics and Biomedicine (BIBM), 2017.
 - 2017 **Denis Newman-Griffis**, Albert M Lai, and Eric Fosler-Lussier. Insights into Analogy Completion from the Biomedical Domain. In *Proceedings of the 16th Workshop on Biomedical Natural Language Processing (BioNLP*), 2017.
 - 2017 **Denis Newman-Griffis** and Eric Fosler-Lussier. Second-Order Word Embeddings from Nearest Neighbor Topological Features. Pre-print: arXiv:1705.08488, 2017.
 - 2016 Denis R Griffis, Chaitanya Shivade, Eric Fosler-Lussier, and Albert M Lai. A Quantitative and Qualitative Evaluation of Sentence Boundary Detection for the Clinical Domain. In Proceedings of the AMIA Summit on Clinical Research Informatics (AMIA-CRI), 2016.

Posters and Presentations

2019 **Denis Newman-Griffis**, Ayah Zirikly, Pei-Shu Ho, Jonathan Camacho Maldonado, Maryanne Sacco, Alex Marr, Albert M Lai, and Eric Fosler-Lussier. Automated classification of mobility activities in free text clinical narratives. Poster presentation, in *Proceedings of the Annual Symposium of the American Medical Informatics Association (AMIA*), 2019.

- 2019 Denis Newman-Griffis. Kickstarting NLP for whole-person activity information with representation learning and data analysis. Thesis proposal, in 2019 Annual Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics, Student Research Workshop, 2019.
- 2018 Denis Newman-Griffis. Natural language processing approaches to extracting patient functioning from clinical data. Invited talk at Stanford University, Center for Population Health Sciences, March 2018.
- 2018 Denis Newman-Griffis, Albert M Lai, and Eric Fosler-Lussier. Jointly embedding biomedical entities and text with distant supervision. Poster presentation, in *Proceedings of the AMIA Informatics Summit*, 2018.
- 2017 Denis Newman-Griffis, Thanh Thieu, Chunxiao Zhou, Diane Brandt, Jonathan Camacho Maldonado, Julia Porcino, Albert M Lai, and Leighton Chan. Characterizing the language of functioning: A corpus analysis illustrating how human function is described in clinical text. Poster presentation, in *Proceedings of the AMIA Summit on Clinical Research Informatics* (AMIA-CRI), 2017.

Education

2014– **PhD student**, *The Ohio State University, Department of Computer Science and Engineering*, Columbus, OH, USA.

Modeling and extracting information regarding patient function from clinical text. Co-advised by Dr. Eric Fosler-Lussier and Dr. Albert Lai (now of Washington University in St. Louis)

2008–2012 Bachelor of Arts, Carleton College, City, Magna cum laude.

Majors: Computer Science & Russian

- o Senior thesis (Computer Science) titled "PIG: Packet Inspection Guru."
- Senior thesis (Russian): translation of Georgiy Demidov's short story, "No Toe Tag," published in the short story collection, "Five Fates from a Wondrous Planet" (2015).

Teaching/Mentoring

- 2018–2019 Advising Brendan Whitaker, OSU Mathematics; Research project on properties of language representations that contribute to downstream tasks.
 - Brendan awarded 3rd place presenter in Statistical and Mathematical Modeling section of 2019 Ohio State Denman Undergraduate Research Forum.
 - Resulted in co-first author paper accepted to RepEval 2019.
- Autumn 2017 CSE 3521 Survey of Artificial Intelligence I: Basic Techniques

 Dept. of Computer Science and Engineering, The Ohio State University

Fellowships

2015– **Pre-Doctoral Fellow**, *National Institutes of Health, Clinical Center*.

Professional Experience

2012–2014 **Software Developer**, *Fulcrum Software Solutions*, Dublin, OH, USA.

Designed, developed, and deployed applications in the business and healthcare sectors, using the .NET development stack.

• Acted as client contact for design and troubleshooting on multiple projects.

Service

Departmental Service

2015–2018 **AI Seminar Coordinator**, *The Ohio State University*, Columbus, OH, USA. Coordinated bi-weekly seminar series for student presentations on ongoing AI research at Ohio State.

Reviewer

- 2019 ACL, AMIA Informatics, AMIA Annual Summit, NAACL Student Research Workshop, BioNLP, EMNLP
- 2018 ACL, AMIA Informatics, AMIA Annual Summit, COLING, ACL Student Research Workshop
- 2017 ACL, AMIA Annual Summit, EMNLP
- 2016 ACL, AMIA Annual Summit

Other

- 2014– **Volunteer Judge**, *Ohio State Science Day*.

 Judged science fair projects of students grades 5–12.
- 2016–2017 President, Columbus Symphony Chorus, Columbus, OH, USA.

Affiliations

- ACL Association for Computational Linguistics
- ACM Association for Computing Machinery
- AMIA American Medical Informatics Association
- ASEE American Society for Engineering Education